let X be a positive real number and
first suppose that X is greater than or
equal to 1 start with a right triangle
with legs of length x and 1 take a
rotated copy and then scale that copy by
the value 1 /x creating a right triangle
with side lengths of 1 and 1 /x the
purple triangle that's pictured has an
area of 1/2 * X while the smaller red
triangle has an area of 1/ 12 *
1/x but now notice that the area of
these two triangles encloses the area of
the 1X one square as shown here and
therefore 1 12 * x + 1 12 * 1/x is
greater than or equal to 1 and
multiplying both sides by 2 we get that
x + 1X is greater than or equal to 2 by
interchanging X and 1 /x we see that
this inequality holds for all positive
real numbers X can you see from the
diagram when equality holds